Guide to the Program on Preparing Minorities for Academic Careers records, 1987-1994
Duke University. University Archives
Program on Preparing Minorities for Academic Careers records 1987-1994
Duke University. University Archives
Program on Preparing Minorities for Academic Careers.
1.5 linear feet Extent: 1000 Items
The Program on Preparing Minorities for Academic Careers was launched in 1989 with a grant from the Charles A. Dana Foundation to Duke University and five historically black colleges and universities: Spelman College, Xavier University, Morehouse College, Hampton University, and Tuskegee University. The program's purpose was to increase the number of minority undergraduate students preparing for careers as college and university professors.
UA.26.03.0018
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Program on Preparing Minorities for Academic Careers records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1994.
Historical Note
The Program on Preparing Minorities for Academic Careers (PMAC) was launched in 1989 with a grant from the Charles A. Dana Foundation to Duke University and five historically black colleges and universities: Spelman College, Xavier University, Morehouse College, Hampton University, and Tuskegee University. The program's purpose was to increase the number of minority undergraduate students preparing for careers as college and university professors. The primary components of the program included student participation in teaching and research, which was supervised by faculty mentors at each college, and summer research terms as well as conferences held at Duke University.
Through an additional grant from the Hearst Foundation, Dillard University joined the program in 1991. The program also received funding from the Commonwealth Fund.
Robert Wright was the first director of the program and he was succeeded by Scotty Elliott in 1991. Both directors were located at Duke University. Funding for the program ended in 1994.
Collection Overview
The collection contains material pertaining to the program's operations and activities at Duke University as well as at the historically black colleges and universities that participated. Present are reports, correspondence, printed material, clippings, and financial records documenting the various facets of the five year effort to educate minority undergraduate students in preparation for careers in college teaching and research. Throughout the records attention is paid to the impact of the program, primarily measured by the students' post-graduate activities. Correspondence and proposals originating from Duke and the Dana Foundation, as well as press releases and clippings provide summary information on the creation and activities of the program.
Student identifiable information is present throughout the majority of the collection and is restricted under FERPA. However, researchers may access the material for use in research as long they agree not to release personally identifiable student information without the prior written consent of the student, and to destroy all student-identifying information at the completion of their research.
Subject Headings
African American universities and colleges; Charles A. Dana Foundation; Minorities -- Education (Higher) -- United States; Minorities -- Vocational guidance -- United States; Program on Preparing Minorities for Academic Careers
Related Material
Black History at Duke Reference Collection, 1948 - 2001 and undated
University Archives, Duke University.
Black on White Steering Committee records, 1988-1989
University Archives, Duke University.
H. Keith H. Brodie, President, Records, 1963 - 1994.
University Archives, Duke University.
Interdisciplinary Studies records, 1998-2006
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 1 Box
  - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - 1990
      - Hampton University (Box 1)
      - Morehouse College: Mid-year and Annual Report (Box 1)
      - Spelman College: Mid-year and Annual Report (Box 1)
      - Tuskegee University: Mid-year and Annual Report (Box 1)
      - Xavier University: Mid-year and Annual Report (Box 1)
    - 1991
      - Hampton University (Box 1)
      - Morehouse College (Box 1)
      - Spelman College (Box 1)
      - Tuskegee University (Box 1)
      - Xavier University (Box 1)
    - 1992
      - Dillard University (Box 1)
      - Hampton University (Box 1)
      - Morehouse College (Box 1)
      - Spelman College (Box 1)
      - Tuskegee University (Box 1)
      - Xavier University (Box 1)
    - 1993
      - Dillard University (Box 1)
      - Hampton University (Box 1)
      - Morehouse College (Box 1)
      - Spelman College (Box 1)
      - Tuskegee University (Box 1)
      - Xavier University (Box 1)
  - Final Financial Reports from Schools (includes 1994 Year end reports], 1994 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Final Evaluations, 1994? (Box 1)
  - Final and Annual Reports from the PMAC Director, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin-Fleishman Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Brodie-Kreidler Correspondence -- Offers and Counter-offers, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Budget Information for Dana Foundation, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Commonwealth Annual Report, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Dana Foundation Program, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Early Dana Foundation Information (historical), 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation/Reporting--General Information, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - News articles, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - News clippings, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - PMAC Winter Conference Programs, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases from Historically Black Colleges and Universities, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases: Dana Foundation, National and North Carolina, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Programming on preparing Minorities for Academic Careers (Box 1)
  - Proposal to the Hearst Foundation--Financial Data, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Proposal for U.S. Dept. of Education [McNair Fellow], 1991 (Box 1)
  - Xavier University--Proposal to Dana Foundation; Award Information, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Xavier University--Financial Aid guidelines, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Year End Financial Statements, 1989-1993 (Box 1)